The vein was falling with a soft but steady persistence upon the gaslit streets of London.
That vast and shadowed city which seemed to brood eternally beneath its pall of smoke and mystery.
It was upon such a night, damp and sullen, that I, Dr. John Watson, was summoned from my own
domestic peace into an adventure whose strange turns and startling revelations yet linger in
my memory with singular vividness. I shall set it down faithfully here, in the hope that those
who follow the exploits of my friend Mr. Sherlock Holmes may find interest in the peculiar case of
the man with the twisted lip. I must begin by confessing that my own role at the outset was
quite unconnected to any investigation. Rather, it was the simple call of friendship and duty
which led me forth into the night. My dear wife, perceiving my concern for a patient who had
slipped grievously in her battle against the malady of opium, had urged me to attend her
even at this late hour, and thus, cloaked and gloved against the damp,
I made my way to the dismal quarter of the city, known as the East End,
where the narrow streets were lined with gin shops and opium dens,
and where the law held but a feeble dominion.
I recall thinking, as I walked beneath the dripping eaves,
how different is this world from that of Baker Street,
where Holmes sits by his fire, cold pipe in hand,
marshalling the facts of some intricate case.
Here, the tragedy is of a humbler, but no less ruinous sort,
the slow poisoning of body and soul. At length I came to the squalid house known to me as one of
ill-repute, where men of all classes, sailors, beggars, and even gentlemen in disguise sought
escape from reality in the deadly fumes of the poppy, with some reluctance I entered,
and found myself amidst the low murmur of voices, the reek of opium, and the dim gimmer of lambs
hung askew upon the peeling walls. The keeper of the den, a lasker of sinister appearance,
greeted me with a knowing smile,
as though accustomed to the sight of respectable men
slinking into his pit of degradation.
I inquired after my patient
and was soon led to the corner
where she lay half-conscious upon a tat-
red couch,
having ascertained her condition
and given what aid I could.
I was about to depart
when my eye was caught by a familiar figure
seated in the shadow,
his long limbs stretched,
his deer-stalker hat pulled low upon his brow.
Holmes, I exclaimed,
scarcely believing my senses.
What in heaven's name are you doing here,
in a place like this?
His thin lips curled into a faint smile
as he drew me nearer with a slight motion of the hand.
Hush, Watson, your voice may carry.
I am engaged upon an inquiry of considerable delicacy,
and this den is, for the moment,
the very heart of my investigation.
But surely, surely such a place is beneath
even your most singular methods.
What can you hope to learn here amidst this degradation?
Elementary, my dear fellow, crime, like disease, must be traced to its breeding grounds.
And here, amongst the smoke and the whispers, men reveal truths they would never speak in the bright light of the strand.
But come, your arrival is not ill-timed. There is more afoot tonight than either of us expected.
He rose swiftly, and with that peculiar energy, which seemed always to animate him in the pursuit of a case,
he guided me from the den and into the street.
The rain had slackened, but the cobblestones gleamed with a treacherous sheen.
A handsome cab was waiting at the corner, its horse stamping impatiently.
Quickly, Watson, a lady of your acquaintance has need of you, and by extension, of me.
We go to Kentish Town. There is no time to lose.
Perplexed but obedient, I climbed into the cab beside him.
The horse sprang forward and the damp night air rushed past as Holmes, ever composed,
produced his clay pipe and filled it with his black shag tobacco.
He puffed once or twice, then turned to me with that piercing gaze which seemed to look to a man's very soul.
Tell me at once what this is about, Holmes. You speak of a lady of my acquaintance. Who can it be?
It is none other than Mrs. St. Clair, the wife of the respectable gentleman of the city.
She is, at this very moment, in a state of the most acute agitation.
She believes her husband has been foully used in the neighbourhood of that very opium den we have just quitted.
Her message reached me not an hour ago, and knowing that your medical obligations might draw you eastward,
Eastward, I took the liberty of seeking you there.
The case, Watson, promises to be one of those puzzles
where the outward appearance is grotesque
and the inward truth stranger still.
Ah?
Mr. St. Clair, I do not recall having met the man.
He is a person of good repute,
engaged in certain mercantile ventures
and known for his probity.
Yet it is in connection with him
that we shall find ourselves in the very thick of London's underworld,
and perhaps face a deception so bold that even I must take care to untangle it.
Thus did Holmes tantalize me with hints, but no more, hey, Sibol,
until at last we reached the modest residence in Kentish Town.
The cab drew up before a neat little villa,
where a light still burned in the window despite the late hour.
As we entered, we were greeted by a lady whose pale countenance and trembling hands
betrayed her distress.
Oh, Mr. Holmes,
thank heaven you have come.
And you too, Dr. Watson.
You are both most kind.
I am nearly beside myself with dread
for I know not whether my husband
be alive or dead.
Holmes bowed with his accustomed courtesy,
but his eyes missed nothing.
The disorder of the room,
the hastily discarded shawl,
the anxious glances toward the door.
Compose yourself, madam.
You have sent for us to aid you, and aid you we shall.
But you must give us every particular without reservation.
Yes, yes, I shall tell you all.
My husband, Neville Sinclair, set out this morning for the city.
He is a most punctual man, and never has he failed to return by evening to his supper.
Yet today he did not come.
In my anxiety, I took it upon myself to go in search of him.
I knew that his business would take him through the east end
and so I made my way there, though it is a place I dread.
She shuddered and I offered her a glass of water,
which she accepted dreadfully before continuing.
It was near to the riverside, in that vile quarter where the opium dens abound,
that I saw him, or thought I saw him, at a window above the sign of the bar of gold.
He was leaning out, and for an instant I caught his face in the lamplight.
I cried out to him, but in that very moment he seemed to be dragged back violently as though by some unseen hand,
and then the window was closed, and I saw him no more.
Good Lord! That is most sinister indeed.
Pray continue, madam, what followed.
I rushed to the place at once, but the last car who keeps the establishment would not admit me.
I was near to fainting when a constable came by, and to him I explained my plight.
Together we forced our way inside, but there was no sign of my husband,
only a most hideous creature, a beggar with a twisted lip sat, crouched among the pillows.
The constable searched him, and found upon his person a few coins and a letter,
and here, here is the last terrible proof.
With trembling hands she drew from her bosom
a small parcel wrapped in paper.
She unfolded it and to our astonishment
there fell upon the table a child's toy,
a wooden block with letters upon it,
smeared with blood.
I recognized it instantly,
for my own children had such playthings.
It is my son's.
Neville carried it with him this morning
to amuse the little one when he returned home.
And now it is stained thus.
Oh, Mr. Holmes, what can it mean?
Holmes took up the toy, examined it minutely, and then set it down.
His face was inscrutable, yet his eyes gleamed with that light I knew so well,
the light of fierce intellectual engagement.
We must go at once to the Bar of Gold, Watson.
The night is not yet spent, and if there is truth to be learned, it lies there.
Mrs. St. Clair caught his sleep with desperate urgency.
Promise me, Mr. Holmes, promise me that you will bring him back to me,
dead or alive, only do not leave me in this torment of uncertainty.
I promise, madam, that I shall leave no stone unturned in my search.
Whether your husband lives or has met some darker fate, you shall have the truth.
And so, without delay, Holmes and I once more plunged into the labyrinth of London by night,
the case unfolding before us like some dreadful enigma whose solution would test even the limits
of his remarkable genius. The handsome cab rattled swiftly over the cobbles as Holmes and I sped
once more toward the east end. The hour was late, and most respectable citizens were long abed,
yet the darker quarters of London seemed to grow only more animated. Women of dishevelled attire
coiled from shadowed doorways, while drunken sailors wheeled arm in arm, singing coarse
songs beneath the dripping lamps. A chill wind rose from the river, carrying with it the mingled
odours of tar, smoke and decay. Holmes, seated opposite me, remained in profound concentration,
his eyes half closed, the toy block turning slowly in his lean fingers as though it held
some secret known only to him. Holmes, do you truly believe Neville St. Clair was abducted
before his wife's very eyes, the idea chins the blood. And yet, might she not have been deceived
by some resemblance, some figure seen dimly through the lamplight? My dear Watson, I never
permit myself the luxury of premature conclusions. Whether Mrs. St. D'Ere, Clare's testimony is
accurate or not, it is an essential fact that she herself believes it true. That alone renders it of
value. Our task is to separate the certain from the conjectural, the proved from the imagined.
And for that, we must examine the bar of gold for ourselves.
At length, the cab drew up beside a crooked alley which sloped down toward the thins.
There, beneath a weathered signboard depicting a gilded chalice, stood the squalid den which
had already played so sinister a part in the day's events. Soon, a solitary lamp flickered
above its door, throwing a fitful glow upon the wet pavement, the Lasker keeper, with his
turban askew, regarded us with sullen suspicion as we entered. Good evening. You recall me,
no doubt. I was here earlier tonight. Yes, Sahib, I remember. But there is nothing here for you now.
No trouble tonight. That remains to be seen. My companion and I shall have a look about.
Do not trouble yourself to follow us.
window overlooking the alley. Holmes crossed at once to that window and examined the sill with
his magnifying lens. The rain had washed it clean, yet I saw him nod with satisfaction as he traced
some faint mark invisible to my eye. Watson, observe here. Though the paint is blistered,
there remains the smudge of a hand. Rest hard against the wood, and see here fibres
quarked upon the latch.
The window was not merely closed,
but shut in great haste.
I do not doubt
Mrs. St. Clair's account.
A husband was indeed here.
But if so, where is he now,
and by whom was he seized?
That, my friend,
is the riddle
we are come to answer.
Yet consider,
the lady described a man
with a twisted lip.
Such a person
is not easily forgotten.
Let us see what manner of fellow he may be.
As though in answer to Holmes' words, the door opened and Constable Barton, a stout young officer,
entered the chamber, his lantern casting long shadows upon the walls.
Good evening, Mr. Holmes. Doctor, you come in good time.
The fellow is secured below and awaits your inspection.
Excellent. And what have you found here?
Nothing of Mr. St. Clair, sir, save for this.
He held up a bundle of clothes, neatly folded, and undeniably of good quality.
Within the coat pocket dimmered a handful of sovereigns,
and in the waistcoat lay a pocketbook bearing the name Neville St. Sane.
Claire.
It is his beyond all doubt, and yet how should his garments be here while he himself has vanished?
A question worthy of our utmost attention.
But let us first behold the occupant of this chamber.
I then said, Anved Daya.
We descended once more and were conducted to a corner where,
upon a heap of rags, crouched as loathsome a creature as ever I beheld.
His face was twisted into a perpetual leer,
his lip drawn awry so as to expose a row of yellow teeth.
Kutishing, a mass of unkempt hair hung about his brow
and his small eyes glittered with mingled fear and defiance.
He clutched a clay pipe in his claw-like hand
and when we approached, he snarled like some cornered animal.
Your name?
They call me Boone, sir.
Hugh, Boone.
Under begging life I lead,
for there's little else for the likes of me.
You occupy this chamber?
Aye, and pay rent for it.
But you will not find your gentleman here.
I know nothing of him.
But his clothes were discovered above.
How do you explain that?
I cannot explain what I never saw.
Maybe he left them, maybe someone blanted them.
All I know is that I mind my own trade, and no harm in it.
His voice was thick and guttural, his manner evasive.
Holmes regarded him with cool detachment,
though I could perceive the keen play of thought behind those sharp grey eyes.
You deny, then, any knowledge of Mr. Neville St. Clair?
And yet, Mrs. St. Clair?
Clair herself avers that she saw her husband at your window
this very evening.
Then the lady is mistaken,
for no man has been here save me.
Holmes turned to the constable.
You have searched the premises thoroughly?
Every inch, sir.
No trace of the missing man,
alive or dead.
And yet here are his garments,
his pocketbook,
his very rings.
Curious indeed.
Boon, you will remain in custody
until further inquiry.
The beggar only shrugged and sank back into his rags, muttering curses under his breath.
Holmes beckoned me aside.
You perceive, Watson, how the case grows darker.
Here we have the undeniable presence of Saint Seyn.
Clare, yet the only occupant of the house is this wretch.
Are we to suppose that he murdered the man and disposed of the body
between the moment his wife cried out and the moment that Constable entered?
Impossible! And yet what other hypothesis presents itself?
Could he have concealed the body somewhere near at hand?
The river-lice clothes might not have been cast into the water?
A plausible thought, but it fails in one regard.
The clothes are here.
Why should a murderer trouble to strip his victim at casting him into the Thames?
No, Watson, there is a deeper artifice at work.
we must return to Baker Street
and there in the light of my study
arrange these facts in proper order
only then shall we hope
to pierce the mystery of the man
with the twisted lip
and so leaving Boone in custody
and the bewildered constable to his duties
we quitted the bar of gold
and once more took to the cab
the streets were near deserted now
and the lamps burned low
as we drove westward
Holmes, siphoned and absorbed
drew his cloak about him
while I turned the matter over
in my own mind, only to find each conjecture ending in contradiction. At last, as the first
pallor of dawn touched the eastern sky, we reached Baker Street. Mrs. Hudson had long since retired,
and so we let ourselves in with a key. Holmes threw himself into his armchair, lit his pipe,
and spread upon the table the array of evidence, the toy block, the garments, the pocketbook,
and his own hasty notes. Then, leaning back, he steepled his fingers beneath his chin and closed
his eyes. Now, Watson, let us review. A gentleman of respectability disappears. His wife beholds him,
as she believes, straddling at a window above an opium den. She raises the alarm. The room
contains only a deformed beggar. The husband's clothing is discovered, but not the man himself.
There is no blood, no weapon, no trace of violence, save in the lady's account.
What explanation can encompass all?
Murder seems the most natural conclusion, yet you yourself dismiss it. Kidnapping, perhaps?
To what end? A man of moderate fortune, no political significance, no known enemies.
And yet, Watson, consider this.
Why should the beggar Boone possess the outward signs of such prosperity?
A room above a den, yes, but also sovereigns in his purse,
a pipe of good quality, and did you mark it?
The clean, well-kept nails of his hands, strange for one who lives in filth.
Indeed, I had not observed that.
It is in such trifles that the truth reveals itself.
I must pursue this line further.
But first, we must rest.
Sleep a few hours, my friend,
and tomorrow we shall follow the twisted lip to its root.
Thus ended that long and bewildering night.
Though for myself, sleep came only in uneasy fragments,
haunted by the image of Mrs. St. Clair's pained face
and the leering visage of the beggar boon,
little did I know what revelations awaited us upon the morrow.
The following day dawned grey and cheerless,
with the fog hanging low over Baker Street, like a heavy curtain.
London, that restless giant, was stirring to life.
But within the quiet walls of our sitting room, the world seemed suspended,
awaiting the unravelling of the strange mystery that had so suddenly enmeshed us.
Holmes had slept, but briefly, rising with the first light.
And I found him already immersed in chemical experiments.
His sleeves rolled back and his sharp profile bent over a retort.
A faint smell of acid mingled with the aroma of coffee Mrs. Hudson had contrived for us.
Holmes, you astonish me.
After such a night, one would expect you to rest.
And here you are at your crucibles, as if a laboratory were more refreshing than a bed.
Rest, my dear Watson, is a relative thing.
My mind was occupied, and until it has reached a point of resolution, the body refuses repose.
Besides, a few hours suffice me where another man might require aid.
But come, sit down.
I have arranged matters in my thoughts and would gladly submit them to your judgment.
I did as he bade me, settling into the familiar armchair opposite,
while Holmes laid aside his retort and, pipe in hand,
began to pace the carpet with that peculiar quick stride which marked his deepest concentration.
Let us begin with certainties.
First, Neville Sane.
Claire was unquestionably in the room above the bar of gold upon the evening in question.
His wife saw him, and her recognition may be accepted as conclusive.
Second, his clothing was found there, complete and in good order.
Third, the only other person present was the beggar Boone.
Fourth, no trace of violence was discovered. These are facts.
Now, how are we to reconcile them?
The most natural supposition, surely,
is that Boone murdered St. Clair and disposed of the body.
You forget, Watson, that the constable entered
within moments of Mrs. St. Clair's alarm.
Could a man commit murder, strip his victim,
conceal or remove the body,
and then resume his place upon the rags?
All in so short an interval?
Third, the hypothesis will not hold.
Then perhaps the body was hidden within the house?
The police searched thoroughly.
Unless we assume supernatural powers of concealment, the body is not there.
Yet, the garments are.
Therefore, one of two conclusions must be drawn, either saint.
Clare left that room alive and by his own will,
or else he never left it at all, but in a manner which defies our conventional categories.
I confess I shook my head at this, for such subtleties of reasoning are not native to my own mind.
If he left alive, then why should he abandon his clothes? It is unthinkable.
Quite so. And yet, Watson, look at Boone.
You noted his appearance, the twisted lick, the wild hair, the rags.
But did you note his hands?
You mentioned them last night. They were cleaner than one would expect.
Precisely. The nails were well-shaped, the fingers tapering.
Not the claws of a vagabond who scrabbles in the gutter, but the hands of a gentleman.
That incongruity, my dear fellow, is the key. Boon is not what he seems.
Holmes spoke with that quiet certainty, which made contradiction futile.
Joke hai! He threw himself once more into his chair and blew a ring of smoke toward the ceiling.
Imagine, Watson, that a man of education and respectability should adopt,
if for purposes of his own, the disguise of a beggar.
What then? He could earn a livelihood, escape recognition,
and vanish at will into the city's teeming crowds.
Might not Boone be such a one?
But to what end? Why should a gentleman debase himself so horribly?
That is the point we must discover.
Yet I have already made one experiment toward it.
He rose, went to his desk and drew forth a sheet of notepaper.
Upon it was scrawled several lines in his bold, angular hand.
This morning I dispatched telegrams to certain agents of mine in the city,
instructing them to gather intelligence upon the beggar.
Boone, where he stations himself, how long he has been known, what manner of life he leads.
Their reports will reach me ere nightfall. Meanwhile, we must wait. In the interval,
I propose we call once more upon Mrs. Saints, Claire, that we may learn whether any further
intelligence has reached her. Accordingly, after a hasty luncheon, we set forth again to
Kentish town. The weather had turned drizzling
and the streets were splashed with puddles.
Mrs. Saint-Saint Lair received
us with anxious eagerness, though her
face was somewhat less stricken than on the
previous night.
Oh, Mr. Holmes, you are kind to come.
I have heard nothing since I last saw you.
My heart tells me
that Neville is still alive,
yet the uncertainty is torture.
You may trust,
madam, that no effort shall be
spared. Permit me a few questions. Your husband, I understand, is in the habit of going daily to
the city? Yes, sir, though his business is of a private sort. He has dealings in shares and such
matters, and keeps an office in the square. Did you ever observe aught unusual in his comings
or goings? Any
acquaintances of whom you disapproved?
Any hint that he lived
a double life?
Never. He was the most affectionate of husbands,
the most devoted of fathers.
He had no secrets from me,
at least so I believed.
You mentioned yesterday
that he carried a chai stoy,
the wooden block stained with blood.
Was that indeed the same which you saw?
Oh yes, doctor.
I gave it him myself, not an
hour before he left the house.
He placed it in his pocket, saying that our little one should have it at bedtime.
To see it return to me in such a condition, it was dreadful.
And on the day of his disappearance, was there anything unusual in his manner?
He was cheerful as always. Nothing gave me cause for alarm.
Holmes listened with grave attention, making brief notes in his pocketbook.
When she had finished, he rose and bowed with the utmost courtesy.
You have aided us greatly, madam. Be assured the truth is nearer than you think.
Watson and I will pursue the inquiry further, and I hope ere long to bring you tidings more certain than hope or fear.
We took our leave, and as we walked back toward the main road, I could not refrain from voicing my perplexity.
Huh!
Horns, the matter grows only darker. The wife swears to her husband's character and to her own vision of him at the window.
yet all material evidence points only to Boone.
How can the two be reconciled?
By assuming that they are not two, but one.
I stared at him in astonishment.
You mean that Boone is Neville St. Clair himself?
Ah, exactly so. Hmm.
But Holmes, that is monstrous.
Why should a gentleman voluntarily assume such a loathsome disguise?
That, Watson, is the very question which makes the case so singular.
Yet remember, the evidence fits.
The clean hands, the sovereigns, the pipe of quality, the well-furnished room.
These are not the belongings of a vagabond.
They belong to a man who plays at vagabondage.
How?
And what is more profitable in London than the trade of a professional beggar?
Boone has been seen daily upon the streets,
and it is whispered that his takings exceed those of many a merchant.
Suppose, then, that Neville's saint, Clare, for reasons of his own,
has for years maintained this double existence,
respectable gentleman by day, mendicant by evening.
Last night his wife stumbled upon his secret.
Her cry brought the police.
He had but moments to effect his transformation.
He thrust his clothes aside and appeared as Boone.
It is a bold theory, but consider how well it answers all difficulties.
Whenever, Tampa, I was struck dumb for the audacity of the idea left me at once bewildered and convinced.
It is incredible, and yet, as you stated, I can scarce resist believing.
And yet, how to prove it?
Proof is what we shall seek.
Boone is in custody.
I have but to obtain certain cosmetic reagents, and we shall see what lies beneath that twisted lip.
Holmes' words thrilled me, for I knew that some decisive revelation was near.
We returned to Baker Street, where the remainder of the afternoon was spent in impatient expectation.
At length, as dusk fell, there came the sound of wheels, and a messenger arrived bearing several envelopes.
Holmes tore them open eagerly, scanning the contents with a gleam of triumph.
It is as I suspected. Boone has been known these seven years at the corner of Threadneedle Street
and is reputed to make his two pounds a day. Yet no one knows where he goes at night.
Some say he has a lodging in Stepney, others that he vanishes into the river fog.
No beggar of his class ever handled so much coin. Watson, the case is solved in all but the formal proof.
And that proof?
We shall obtain it tonight
Come, the yard awaits us
Bring your revolver
Though I think we shall need no force
Beyond a pair of sharp eyes
And a bottle of spirits
And so, as night closed once more upon London
We set forth with renewed vigour
Bound for the police station
Where Boone, the man with the twisted lip
Awaited the final stroke of Holmes' deduction
The night was heavy with fog
When we left Baker Street
Hide and piety
Asif, the lamps along the thoroughfare
Dewing faintly like beacons
Half lost in a sea of grey
Didi, Combs was in a state of quiet
But intense excitement
His long fingers twitching restlessly upon his gain
His eyes gleaming with that peculiar fire
Which betrayed the near approach of discovery
Hi, for my part
Felt a mingling of eagerness and unease
For though I had come to trust his instincts implicitly
The notion that a respectable gentleman
Could also be a loathsome beggar
Seemed almost beyond the bounds of human tradulity
Our cab bore us swiftly eastward to Bow Street
where Boone was confined
The police, accustomed now to Holmes' interventions
admitted us without demur
We were ushered into a plain chamber
lit by a single oil lamp
where at a table sat Inspector Bradstreet
a burly officer of frank and genuine manner
Beside him, slouched in his chair
was the miserable figure of Boone
His twisted mouth contorted in a sneer
His eyes darting from one to another of us
with sullen defiance
Good evening, Mr. Holmes
Dr. Watson, I thought it but fair to let you have a look at our prisoner.
He's as obstinate as a mule.
Won't give us a word beyond his name.
What's more, we've no charge to hold him on, save suspicion.
If we can't prove art against him, he'll walk free in the morning.
That would be a pity, Inspector,
for I believe this man's true identity to be of the first importance.
If you will grant me a few minutes alone with him,
I promise you the strangest transformation you have ever witnessed within these walls.
Gnarling transformation, is it?
You may waste your time, sir, but I am what I am.
A poor cripple with a cursed lip.
And that's the end of it.
We shall see.
Inspector, with your leave, I should like a basin of warm water, a bar of soap, and a small bottle of spirits of heart horn.
You may add a towel, if you are so disposed.
Laughing? By George, Mr. Holmes, this grows curious indeed.
Very well, you shall have your wish.
The required items were soon brought, and Holmes set them meekly upon the table.
He removed his coat, rolled back his sleeves and regarded the prisoner with an expression at once cold and commanding.
Now Boone, or should I say Neville St. Clair, let us dispense with pretense.
You have played your part admirably, but the curtain must fall.
Will you revere yourself or must I do it for you?
At the sound of his true name, Boone started violently.
For an instant, his eyes betrayed panic.
Then he folded his arms with affected composure.
You talk nonsense, sir. I never heard that name before.
So be it. Watson, kindly hold the basin.
With that, Holmes seized the man's chin in his firm grasp, heedless of his struggles,
and began vigorously to scrub the distorted lip with the soapy cloth.
The prisoner writhed and cursed, but Holmes' grip was unyielding.
Presently, with a few rapid motions and a dash of the sharp-smelling spirits,
the grime and pigment yielded and the hideous layer faded.
Beneath the twisted mouth appeared the well-formed features of a man of education and refinement.
The coarse hair was dragged away to reveal a smooth brow,
and the rags seemed suddenly incongruous upon a body that bore itself with the instinctive carriage of a gentleman.
Inspector Bradstreet sprang to his feet with an exclamation of amazement.
By heaven! It is St. Clair himself!
I too was struck speechless, for there before us sat, trembling and abashed,
The very image of the missing gentleman whom we had sought in vain
The transformation was so complete, so astounding
That for a moment I could scarce believe my eyes
Gentlemen, I will confess, resistance is useless
You are torn from me the secret I had hoped to guard to my grave
Yes, I am Neville St. Saint
Claire, though in this garb I am better known as Hugh Boone
It is well, sir, that you acknowledge the truth
Your wife's distress has been grievous
and it is our duty to set her mind at rest.
You owe us, therefore, a full and frank account of your strange deception.
Sindham, Claire buried his face in his hands for a moment,
then raised it with an expression of mingled shame and resignation.
You shall know all.
There is nothing criminal in my conduct, save the deceit of a double life.
When first I came to London, I found myself with modest means and no certain prospect.
effect. One day, in a spirit of idle curiosity, I disguised myself as a beggar, and took a
seat upon the steps of the exchange. To my amazement, I received more alms in a single
day than I could have earned in a week by honest labour. The temptation proved too strong.
I perfected my disguise, altered my lip with a twist of wax and pigment, and soon found
that I could command an income such as many a merchant might envy. By day, I lived as
Neville St. Clair, a gentleman of respectability. By evening I became Boone, the crippled mendicant,
haunting the thoroughfares and filling my purse with the careless charity of passers-by.
But sir, surely you've had shame at such a deception?
At first, doctor, I did indeed. Yet the gold was heavy in my pocket, and as the years passed,
I grew accustomed to the part. I told myself that I wronged no man, that I but accepted
what they freely gave. And in truth, I prospered. I built my house in Kentish Town. I married.
I became a father. None suspected, save the wretched Lusca who let me the room above his den,
where I might transform myself unseen. And last night?
Ah, last night was my undoing. I had donned my disguise as usual and was in the act of changing
in the room above the bar of gold when suddenly i heard my wife's voice in the street below she had seen me at the window ere i could withdraw in my panic i dragged myself back closed the sash and flung off my gentleman's clothes at that instant the constable burst in
i had but a moment to thrust the garments aside and resume the semblance of boon they found me thus and i held stubbornly to the part i never dreamed that holmes would pierce the veil so swiftly
and the blood upon the toy block.
A trifle.
I had cut my finger as I strove in haste
to conceal my appearance.
The toy was in my pocket
and so it was stained.
I swear, there was no violence, no crime,
save my own duplicity.
Inspector Bradstreet shook his head in astonishment.
Well, I'll be bound.
In all my days, I've never seen the like.
You think that a respectable gentleman
should masquerade thus?
But as no crime has been committed,
Sabre fraud upon the public, I cannot hold you further.
You are free, sir.
Though I dare say you'll find your reputation in peril should this tale become known.
Inspector, Mr. Holmes, Dr. Watson, I implore you, keep this secret from the world.
My wife and children, let them not suffer for my folly.
I give you my word, I shall never again don this loathsome garb.
The Holmes regarded him sternly for a moment, then softened.
Your punishment, sir, lies in the shame you feel and in the confidence you have betrayed.
I shall not add to it by public exposure.
The truth shall remain among ourselves, provided you keep your oaths.
Go then, and live henceforth as Neville St. Clair, the honest gentleman.
But remember, the eye of conscience is sharper than mine, and it will follow you wheresoever you go.
St. Clair bowed his head in silent gratitude, and the matter was thus concluded.
Yet as we quitted the police station and stepped once more into the foggy street,
I could not refrain from expressing my wonder.
Holmes, this is the strangest case we have yet encountered.
Who could have believed that a man would lead so double a life and for so base a reason?
It is but another proof, Watson, that truth is ever stranger than fiction.
The world is full of masks and deceptions, and it is the task of the detective to tear them away.
In this instance, the mask was literal, and the truth lay beneath a smear of pigment and a twist of wax, elementary, once the cue was grasped.
But to Mrs. Saint, clear. The truth will be joy, and that, I think, is satisfaction enough.
We rode back to Baker Street in thoughtful silence,
while the city slumbered beneath its pall of mist,
and thus ended the case of The Man with the Twisted Lip,
a case which, for sheer singularity of circumstance,
stands unmatched in my long association with Sherlock Holmes.
The fog had lifted somewhat by the time we returned to Baker Street,
though the air was still damp with the lingering breath of the Thames.
Holmes, silent and contemplative, hung his coat upon the peg,
lit the lamp, and flung himself into a familiar chair by the fire,
followed, sinking wearily into my accustomed seat.
The events of the last hours,
the confrontation, the revelation,
the strange confession,
still weighed heavily upon my mind.
Holmes, I can scarcely believe it even now
to think that a man could live such a double life
and that beneath the tatters of a beggar
there should lurk a respectable gentleman.
It is as though one of Dickens' tears
had sprung to life before our very eyes.
You are right, Watson.
It is a tale for the penny magazines.
Yet it illustrates a principle I have long held
that appearances are but the surface of things
and that beneath the mask of poverty may lie the craft of wealth
even as beneath the guise of wealth may lurk the gunning of crime.
In short, we must reason from facts, not from preconceptions.
He leaned back, the smoke from his pipe,
reading about his aesthetic features.
You see, the case was not truly so impenetrable as it appeared.
There was no murder, no abduction, no supernatural disappearance,
merely a clever disguise, sustained by long practice.
The clean hands betrayed him, the sovereigns gave him away,
and the speed with which he transformed himself in that chamber was the final proof.
All was elementally once one permitted oneself to think of the possibility
And yet, Holmes, do you not feel some measure of pity for the man?
His shame, his secrecy, the terror of exposure
Must it not have weighed upon him heavily through the years?
No doubt, Watson, but pity is not my trade
I concern myself with truth
And it is for the man himself to reckon with conscience
Still, I am not inhuman. I agreed to keep his secret, for the sake of his innocent wife and children.
Their happiness outweighs the satisfaction of public justice in this instance.
Let the man bury Boone with his own hands, and may Neville's saint, Clare, henceforth, walk an honest road.
For a time we sat in silence, the fire crackling softly in the grate.
i thought of mrs st claire waiting even now in her little villa at kentish town her heart torn between dread and hope at length i could bear it no longer holmes surely we should carry her the tidings at once it is cruer to let her pass another hour in uncertainty
spoken like a true dr watson ever with an eye to the patient's suffering very well we shall go together a cab will take us swiftly and perhaps you may play the herald of glad news
And so, despite the lateness of the hour, we set forth once more.
The streets were quieter now, the lands burning low, but the city never sleeps entirely.
Soon we stood once more before the modest villa.
Holmes bade me be the one to knock.
And when Mrs. Bezala, mm, Saint Mum, Claire herself answered,
candle in hand, her face pale with long vigils, I took her trembling hand in mine.
Madam, be comforted.
Your husband lives and is safe, tinklers his self.
His absence was not the work of violence.
but of his own most singular deception.
He will return to you this very night,
penitent, and resolved to cast off forever
the mask which has so tormented you.
Best!
All is well.
At these words, she uttered a cry of joy,
and the candle merely fell from her grasp.
Tears streamed down her cheeks
as she pressed my hand to her lips.
Oh doctor, you bring me back to life.
Tell me no more.
I ask no questions.
If Neville lives and will return,
that is all I need.
God bless you and God bless Mr. Holmes.
Wand
We left her thus.
Her heart lightened.
Her candle held high as do it were the lamp of hope itself.
Holmes said nothing as we re-entered the cab
but his eyes softened and I thought I perceived in him a rare glow of satisfaction.
Back at Baker Street, as dawn broke pale and worn across the housetops
Holmes stretched himself upon the sofa and closed his eyes.
Another case concluded.
Watson
Strange, grotesque, perhaps even sordid, but instructive.
Let it stand in your notes as an example of the power of disguise
and of the folly of assuming that poverty must always be genuine.
There is no such school of imposture as London itself.
It breeds deceits in every alley,
and it is our task to tear away the mask, whether it hides crime or folly.
I shall set it down faithfully, Holmes
And though some may find it less sensational than murder or conspiracy
I venture to think that readers will find it no less remarkable
Smiling faintly
Then my work has not been in vain
For if the tale instructs one mind
Sharpens one perception
Or lifts one veil of ignorance
It has served its purpose
And now, Watson, to bed
The next telegram may summon us to some fresh absurdity
and we must be ready.
logic. Beneath his keen deductions lay a thread of mercy, a willingness to temper justice
with compassion when the innocent might suffer by too rigid an application of law. That,
perhaps, was the truest revelation of all. And so I close this record as the lamps of
Baker Street fade into memory and the figure of my friend stands once more before me. Lean,
ascetic, pipe in hand, his eyes alight with that flame of intellect which burned so steadily
and which cast its glow upon many a darkened corner of the human soul,